If you asked me to make list of bands
that I think are tragically overlooked,
...it would be a pretty long list,
...but Cardiacs would sit at the top of it.
Not just because their music is superb,
...a massive cut above most of their
contemporaries in the '80s and '90s,
...but also because of their history
of bravery, variety and individuality.
This is a band cited as an influence
by acts as diverse as:
Radiohead,
...Blur,
...Super Furry Animals,
...Napalm Death and
...Mike Patton.
But despite this,
...their history contains an
unusual amount of misfortune,
...culminating in a tragic ongoing situation
that prompted me to make this video.
But before I get into that,
...let me tell you a little bit more about Cardiacs.
I discovered this band
...when I was studying a master's in composition at
the Royal Conservatoire of Scotland a few years ago.
I was sitting with the head of the department,
...Gordon McPherson,
(speaking of talents that I think
deserve to be better known)
...and we were listening to
something I’d created as a joke -
An interlude in a larger piece I was writing at the time:
And when this was over, Gordon said:
"Hmm..."
"Sounds like Cardiacs."
"Who're they?"
"You don't know Cardiacs?"
"Er... no, um... no"
"No, never heard of the Cardiacs."
"No, no."
"Not 'The Cardiacs'."
"Just 'Cardiacs'."
So we launched YouTube,
...and Gordon put on this:
Now, at this point, I wasn’t quite aware
of how diverse Cardiacs were,
...and just assumed that their schtick
was to dress like homeless clowns
...and play standard pop with zany instrumentation.
But then, around the second chorus,
...the moment when I usually begin to think,
"Yeah, right. Verse/chorus/verse/chorus."
"This song is basically winding down",
...it suddenly went on what I can only describe
...as a virtuoso compositional journey:
Now, despite the mix of nutty
instrumentation and ridiculous visuals,
...this is seriously well-written music.
One of the hardest things to do in pop music
...is constantly change direction
without breaking the sense of flow.
And this sequence flows beautifully.
The best you could hope for from one of
the elite prog rock bands at the time,
...but delivered with casual disdain and
a complete lack of self-importance.
And the more I looked,
...the more there was on offer.
Electrifying fast-paced punk:
Catchy indie songs with complex harmonies:
Synthy electro music:
And whatever style you’d call this:
And then there’s what might be my
favourite rock anthem of all time:
A song called 'Dirty Boy',
...which, if you do nothing else,
...you should listen to in full:
In terms of genre,
...this band are impossible to nail down,
...an artistic freedom afforded to them
by owning their own label called:
But where independence gets you freedom,
...it’s also a very hard road financially.
I’ll get back to this in a moment.
Now, despite their wide variety of styles,
...it’s actually pretty easy to identify Cardiacs
...by common elements in their musical vocabulary.
First, they use a lot of whole tones,
...which often gives the effect
of being in the Lydian mode,
...where the 4th of a major scale is sharpened:
If we play that backwards from the 5th note,
...you have a vocal line in the song ‘Odd Even’.
Then there’s the use of what’s called:
...exemplified in the chorus of
the song 'Jibber and Twitch',
...where the music jumps between
fitting 6 beats in a bar
...to only 4 in a bar:
And then there’s what the blogger Dan Schmidt calls
...the ‘Cardiacs Cadence’:
A flat 3rd,
...followed by a minor 5th,
...followed by a 1st.
This progression is everywhere!
One of the reasons this particular
progression is so compelling
...is that it’s not intuitively obvious what key we’re in,
...which prevents the music from feeling like
it’s landed on a definitive ‘home’ chord.
And while studying this cadence,
...I noticed that those last two examples
shared a chord in common:
E major.
In the song ‘Odd Even’,
...it serves as a 1st,
...whereas in 'Dirty Boy',
...it functions as a flat 3rd.
So I decided to try a little experiment.
I linked these two cadences together,
...and then extended it by imagining the 1st of 'Dirty Boy'
...to be the flat 3rd of a new sequence,
...and then the 1st of that new sequence
...to be a flat 3rd of yet another sequence.
And at this point,
...we’ve looped back to the chord we started on:
This is an extension of what’s called
...the 'mode of limited transposition',
...championed by the composer Olivier Messiaen.
The result is distinctively Cardiac-y sounding,
...and gives us a hint at how Tim Smith manages to
write music that achieves such harmonic agility.
Another notable thing about this band
is their fiercely loyal fan base.
If you start looking into relevant social
media groups or upcoming tribute events,
...you’ll see what I mean.
However, they’ve also provoked extreme dislike too.
In 1984, they were asked by the
band Marillion to join them on tour.
A fantastic opportunity to boost their profile,
...but had to pull out prematurely due to
a violent reaction by Marillion fans
...who pelted them with bottles and
other missiles on multiple occasions.
Years later, when invited to support Blur,
...a band they’d heavily influenced,
...they were greeted with a similar
level of antipathy from Blur fans.
There have also been examples of
very rough treatment in the press too.
In 1987,
...The Sunday Sport, a tabloid rag,
...ran an article about Tim Smith
and his wife Sarah Smith,
...claiming they were siblings engaging
in an incestuous relationship.
There are also claims that an editor of the publication
...deliberately blacklisted the band
...by refusing to mention them in a
good light under any circumstances,
...although I can’t verify this story with certainty.
I can find only one book that makes this claim,
...along with a few examples of mean-spirited reviews.
A particularly savage one by Jack O'Neill,
...summarised with the following words:
How very clever and insightful, Jack.
Cardiacs have also had some pretty bad luck too.
In 1992, they signed a deal to distribute
one of their albums through:
...who almost immediately afterwards
announced bankruptcy,
...resulting in stores not being able
to stock or order the album.
This left Cardiacs owing thousands
of pounds in recording costs.
But the real tragedy of this band occurred
...just after Tim Smith had been to see a
My Bloody Valentine concert in June 2008.
On his way home, he suffered a massive cardiac arrest,
...leading to hypoxic brain damage
before he could be revived.
This severely limited his mobility, dexterity and speech,
...while causing him continuous physical pain.
He has been in care ever since while his
family and friends continue to raise funds
...in the hope of finding a medical or surgical
option that would improve his condition.
One of the main sources of funding for his care
...comes from sales of CDs, DVDs,
...vinyl and other merchandise
available from their website:
Cardiacs.net
If ever there was a reason to buy
physical copies of music, this is it.
The experience of receiving packages
from this site is quite unique
...and also kind of sweet,
...since updates on orders are usually
given by a person called ‘Mary’,
...who to my mind has become the
unofficial mascot of the band.
And if you’re lucky, you might even
get a little handwritten note too.
This is where the fans of the
Cardiacs have to be applauded,
...since they drive demand for the merchandise
...by constantly spreading
word of mouth on social media.
Even more impressive than this
...was their response to a donation
campaign set up at the start of 2018
...to pay for improved care for Tim
...which, it was hoped,
...would help him regain control of his body.
The original figure set at £40,000
was passed within 24 hours,
...leading to it being raised to £100,000
...to fund his treatment for a full year.
As of this moment, the campaign
has achieved 86% of its target.
However, on the 15th of January,
Mary posted on the Cardiacs website to let us know that
...Tim recently had to return to hospital.
To quote one line:
This is quite a distressing thing to read,
...and I can only wish Tim the very best.
And I hope he manages to achieve
his goal of returning to a normal life.
If you find the Cardiacs are to your taste
...and you want to help contribute
towards Tim’s donation campaign
...or just buy a record,
...I put the relevant link in the video description below.
Remember, even buying one of
the records will go a long way.
Tim Smith has left us with a broad
catalogue of fantastic music
...that I think deserves more
recognition than it currently gets.
This is a man who forged his own path
...and inspired countless others to do the same.
Personally, I’ll always remember the
first day I came across his work,
...and wondered to myself:
"Who is this absolute lunatic,"
"...and where can I see more of him?"